Inventory of the Wiktor Sukiennicki papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Wiktor Sukiennicki papers
1914-1993
XX307
Hoover Institution Archives
31 manuscript boxes (12.7 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, notes, reports, radio broadcast transcripts, and printed matter relating to twentieth-century Polish history, the history of the Communist International, and Radio Free Europe broadcasting to Poland. Includes draft and finished reports of the Polish Rada Ministrów, 1946, relating to the Katyn Forest Massacre and Polish prisoners of war in the Soviet Union during World War II.
Sukiennicki, Wiktor, 1901-1983.
Poland. Rada Ministrów.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Polish-American historian and political scientist; research analyst, Radio Free Europe, 1952-1959.
Sukiennicki, a Polish legal scholar and later a research fellow at the Hoover Institution, was the principal investigator of the Katyn Forest Massacre on behalf of the Polish government in exile.
Scope and Content of Collection
Speeches and writings, correspondence, notes, reports, radio broadcast transcripts, and printed matter relating to twentieth-century Polish history, the history of the Communist International, and Radio Free Europe broadcasting to Poland. Includes draft and finished reports of the Polish Rada Ministrów, 1946, relating to the Katyn Forest Massacre and Polish prisoners of war in the Soviet Union during World War II.
The collection's original order and folder titles have been maintained.
Poland--History--20th century.; World War, 1914-1918--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; Communist International.; Radio Free Europe.; Radio broadcasting--Poland.; Katyn Massacre, Katynʹ, Russia, 1940.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons.; Prisoners of war.
- "Facts and Documents Concerning Polish Prisoners of War Captured by the U.S.S.R. During the 1939 Campaign," Council of Ministers, 1946 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- "Facts and Documents Concerning Polish Prisoners of War Captured by the U.S.S.R. During the 1939 Campaign," Council of Ministers, English translation proof, 1946 (Box-folder 1: 2-5)
- "The Mass Murder of Polish Prisoners of War in Katyn," Council of Ministers, 1946 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  Scope and Contents note
  A short report based on "Facts and Documents Concerning Polish Prisoners of War Captured by the U.S.S.R. During the 1939 Campaign," published by the Council of Ministers.
- Polish original text, part I, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 7-9)
  Includes three volumes of handwritten and typed notes from an unknown publication.
- Polish original text, part II, 1941 (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
- Polish original text, part III, 1943-1949 (Box-folder 2: 3-6)
- Polski Czerwony Krzyż w Katyniu, 1946 (Box-folder 2: 7)
- Additional materials, Katyn massacre, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 2: 8-10)
  Materials include copies of printed notes found on victims' bodies from the Katyn massacre and depositions from surviving officers.
- Additional materials, part II, 1946 (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
- Additional materials, part III, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 3: 3-5)
- Additional materials, part IV, 1946-1952 (Box-folder 3: 6-8)
- Wajs, 12-IV [12 April], 1939 (Box-folder 3: 9)
- Dyjas, 1 IX- 31 XII [1 September - 31 December], 1939 (Box-folder 3: 10)
- Siwicki, 9-I [9 January], 1939 (Box-folder 3: 11)
- Trepiak, 22-IV [22 April], 1939-1940 (Box-folder 3: 12)
- Wajda, 12-IV [12 April], 1939 (Box-folder 3: 13)
- Zięcina, 22-IV [22 April], 1939 (Box-folder 3: 14)
- Professor Pieńkowski, 9-IV [9 April], 1939 (Box-folder 3: 15)
- Kruk, 9 IV [9 April], 1940 (Box-folder 3: 16)
- Dr. Jakubowicz, 22-IV [22 April], 1939 (Box-folder 3: 17)
- Solski, 9-IV [9 April], 1939 (Box-folder 3: 18)
- Research studies, Wiktor Sukiennicki, list of publications, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 4: 1)
- Research studies 1-5, 1962 (Box-folder 4: 2-3)
- Research studies 6-10, 1962 (Box-folder 4: 4)
- Research studies 11-16, 1963 (Box-folder 4: 5-6)
- Research studies 17-21, 1964 (Box-folder 4: 7-8)
- "East Central Europe During World War I: From Foreign Domination to National Independence," typescript, undated (Box-folder 5: 1-5)
- Narodowy Komitet Paryski, undated (Box-folder 5: 6)
- "East Central Europe...," typescript in Polish, footnotes, undated (Box-folder 5: 7-8)
- "East Central Europe...," part I, galleys, undated (Box-folder 6: 1-2)
- "East Central Europe...," galleys, undated (Box-folder 6: 3-6)
- "East Central Europe...," notes, galleys, undated (Box-folder 6: 7-8)
- "East Central Europe...," general, 1983 (Box-folder 6: 9-10)
- "Congress of Vienna Aftermath," typed essay, undated (Box-folder 7: 1)
- "Towards the World War," typed essay, undated (Box-folder 7: 2)
- "During the Russian German War," typed essay, undated (Box-folder 7: 3-4)
- "March 1917, Revolution," typed essay, undated (Box-folder 7: 5)
- "November 1917, Revolution and the Peace of Brest," typed essay, undated (Box-folder 7: 6-8)
- "Last Phases of World War I," typed essay, undated (Box-folder 7: 9-10)
- Miscellaneous, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  Handwritten notes, typed essays, a resume, and other documents related to Sukiennicki’s academic career at the Hoover Institution.
- "East Central Europe..," correspondence, proofreading, 1983 (Box-folder 8: 2)
- "East Central Europe...," bibliographic and other material, undated (Box-folder 8: 3-4)
- Book, undated (Box-folder 8: 5-8, 9: 1)
  Includes handwritten notes, chapter outlines, and footnotes from an unknown publication.
- Address book, 1959 (Box-folder 9: 2)
- Wiktor Sukiennicki, undated (Box-folder 9: 3)
  Biographical materials, including a resume, biography, publication list, work timeline, and articles related to Sukiennicki's academic achievements.
- Property in England, 1947 (Box-folder 9: 4)
  Includes expense reports, balance sheets, profit and loss accounts.
- Biography, curriculum vitae, 1983 (Box-folder 9: 5)
  Written by Maciej Siekierski, curator of the European Collections at the Hoover Institution Library & Archives.
- Correspondence, 1928-1989
  - 1962-1968 (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - 1966-1969 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - Family and son, 1959-1961 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - 1959-1980 (Box-folder 9: 9)
  - Sukiennicki, Bohdan, 1945-1950 (Box-folder 9: 10)
  - 1980-1983 (Box-folder 9: 11)
  - Milosz, C., 1961-1989 (Box-folder 9: 12)
  - A-L, 1959-1973 (Box-folder 10: 1-2)
  - Szkota nauk politycznych i spot, 1949-1957 (Box-folder 10: 3)
  - Giedroyc, J., 1951-1970 (Box-folder 10: 4)
  - Wraga, R., 1958-1961 (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - Weintraub, W., 1962-1967 (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - N-Z, 1959-1972 (Box-folder 10: 7)
  - Family, 1941-1952 (Box-folder 10: 8)
  - Dabulewicz, Jadwiga, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 10: 9)
  - Family and son, 1951-1958 (Box-folder 10: 10, 11: 1-2)
  - General, 1945-1972 (Box-folder 11: 3-5)
  - Family
    - 1950-1964 (Box-folder 11: 6-7)
    - 1965-1968 (Box-folder 11: 8-9)
    - 1969-1971 (Box-folder 12: 1-2)
    - 1965-1975 (Box-folder 12: 3-4)
  - Miscellaneous
    Miscellaneous items include article clippings, pamphlets printed in Polish, typescripts, newsletters, and correspondence. A small portion of the materials relate to Sukiennicki's academic career at the Hoover Institution.
    - 1928-1958 (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - 1958-1965 (Box-folder 12: 6)
    - 1965-1967 (Box-folder 12: 7)
- Radio Free Europe (RFE) Polish Desk programs, Munich, 1952 (Box-folder 12: 8-10)
- RFE, 1953 (Box-folder 13: 1)
  Includes typed radio program transcripts and handwritten notes.
- Printed material, 1939-1964 (Box-folder 13: 2)
  Includes printed booklets in English, Polish, and Russian. Subject matter relates to France, Poland, and Russia at the beginning of World War II and American diplomatic relations with Soviet Socialist Republics.
- Duplicate payments and overpayments, 1947-1959 (Box-folder 13: 3)
- Institute for the Study of the USSR reports, 1953-1963 (Box-folder 13: 4-5, 14: 1-4)
- Speeches, part I, 1951-1961 (Box-folder 15: 1-2)
- Speeches, part II, 1940-1963 (Box-folder 15: 3-4)
- RFE, European Federation, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 15: 5-6)
- Correspondence, R.F.E., trip to the USA, 1951-1967 (Box-folder 15: 7-8)
- RFE, programs, general, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 16: 1)
- RFE, Polish Desk programs, Munich, 1953-1958 (Box-folder 16: 2-9, 17: 1)
- RFE, radio program transcripts, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 17: 2-8)
- RFE, English translations, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 18: 1)
- Books and collections, review, undated (Box-folder 18: 2)
- Lectures, University of Oregon, 1962 (Box-folder 18: 3-4)
- Skrypty do wykładów, 1944-1957 (Box-folder 18: 5-7)
- Współczesne problemy społeczeństwa polskiego, 1950 (Box-folder 18: 8-10)
- "Przełom," Wilno, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 19: 1-2)
- Polish-Russian relations throughout history, 1975-1981 (Box-folder 19: 3)
- General, 1947-1985 (Box-folder 19: 4-6)
  Handwritten notes, typescripts, newspaper clippings and pamphlets from Droga, Nad Odrą i Bałtykiem, and Nowogródek. Materials relate to Khrushchev’s accession to power following Stalin’s death and include other post-World War II politics in Europe and America.
- Printed material, 1919-1943 (Box-folder 19: 7)
  Includes copies of book excerpts about the Russian Revolution and the Paris Peace Conference. Printed in English, Russian, French, and German.
- General, 1963-1967 (Box-folder 19: 8)
  Pamphlets, typescripts, and handwritten notes related to Poland during World War II.
- Kukułka, 1950-1967 (Box-folder 19: 9-10)
- Izvestia, 1939 (Box-folder 20: 1)
- "Documents on British Foreign Policy 1919-1939," Polska, 1961 (Box-folder 20: 2-4)
- Szwestia, 1939 (Box-folder 20: 5)
- Printed material, 1917-1980 (Box-folder 20: 6-10)
  Includes typescripts, essays, notes, and book excerpts relating to the Paris Peace Conference and the political aftermath in Russia and Germany.
- Comintern, 1921-1922 (Box-folder 21: 1-2)
- Polish-Soviet relations, 1939-1943 (Box-folder 21: 3)
- Voina, khronika i otkliki, 1914 (Box-folder 21: 4)
- Paris Peace Conference, writings, 1919-1936 (Box-folder 21: 5-6)
- Printed material, 1921-1976 (Box-folder 21: 7-8)
  Photocopies of book excerpts regarding the rise of communism and fascism during the years before World War II. Printed in English, French, German, and Polish.
- "The Baltic Countries, Lithuania and the Ukraine after Brest," typescript, undated (Box-folder 21: 9)
- Comintern, Fascism in 1920s Italy, march on Rome 1922, undated (Box-folder 22: 1)
- Comintern, national-colonial question, 1966 (Box-folder 22: 2)
- Comintern, Fourth Congress, undated (Box-folder 22: 3-4)
- Comintern, minor front organizations, 1968 (Box-folder 22: 5-6)
- Comintern, Soviet press, 1918-1933 (Box-folder 22: 7)
- International communist movement in the 1920s, papers, typescripts, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 22: 8)
- "The American Native Communism,", 1965 (Box-folder 22: 9, 23: 1)
- British Revolutionary Press, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 23: 2-6)
- Belorussia, brochures, 1953-1974 (Box-folder 23: 7)
- Belaruski Golas, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 23: 8)
- Belarus, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 24: 1)
- Bulgaria, upheaval, 1918-1923 (Box-folder 24: 2-3)
- Bulgaria, "Communist Putsch," typed essay, 1967 (Box-folder 24: 4)
- Research studies, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 24: 5)
- Periodicals, Polish, émigré, 1951-1954 (Box-folder 24: 6)
- Soviet periodicals, topics related to Poland, 1920-1925 (Box-folder 24: 7)
- Indices of Soviet periodicals, 1944-1951 (Box-folder 25: 1)
- Kommunismus, 1920, articles related to Poland, 1920-1957 (Box-folder 25: 2)
- Soviet press, transcripts, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 25: 3-5)
- Lenin, works, 1915-1922 (Box-folder 25: 6-7)
- Russian Communist Party, 1924 (Box-folder 25: 8)
- Soviet Union, internal and external politics, 1954 (Box-folder 25: 9)
- Abramovich, Mensheviks and Socialist international, parts I and II, 1956 (Box-folder 26: 1-2)
- Excerpts, undated (Box-folder 26: 3)
  Includes material from Arms of Valor and The Communist Party: An Outline of History. Also includes additional excerpts from unknown publications. Printed in English and Polish.
- Comintern, 1919-1925 (Box-folder 26: 4)
- Kommunisticheskii International, Moscow, 1924 (Box-folder 26: 5)
- American Communist, Chicago, 1919 (Box-folder 26: 6)
- Rote Fahne, Berlin, 1923 (Box-folder 26: 7)
- Soviet press on Poland, 1920-1925 (Box-folder 26: 8)
- Interallied mission in Poland, 1919 (Box-folder 26: 9)
- Narodowy Komitet Paryski, 1919 (Box-folder 27: 1-3)
- Polish-Lithuanian relations, 1918-1921 (Box-folder 27: 4-5)
- 2-Oddziat, reports, 1919 (Box-folder 27: 6-7)
- Articles, Polish-Soviet War, undated (Box-folder 27: 8)
- Articles, Polish-Soviet War (as published by Bellona), 1919-1921 (Box-folder 27: 9-10)
- Soviet annexation of East Poland, 1939-1941 (Box-folder 28: 1-2)
- London, Ministry of Justice, Poland post-war judicial system, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 28: 3-4)
- Deportations from Baltic states, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 28: 5)
- Po Prostu, periodicals, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 28: 6)
- Polish émigré press, includes Communist publication, 1944-1948 (Box-folder 28: 7-8)
- Polish émigré press, 1940-1952 (Box-folder 29: 1)
  Publications include Równośc-Egalite, Robotnik, Tydzień Polski and Dziennik Polski.
- Émigré organizations, 1950-1970 (Box-folder 29: 2)
- Biała księga, 1964 (Box-folder 29: 3)
- Government in exile, releases, 1959-1963 (Box-folder 29: 4)
- Polish constitution, history of, 1942 (Box-folder 29: 5)
- Poland, constitution, 1952 (Box-folder 29: 6)
- Jews, undated (Box-folder 29: 7)
  Includes typed excerpts from various unknown publications covering the Jewish population in Poland.
- "Legenda i rzeczywistość," writings, undated (Box-folder 29: 8)
- "The Comitern and Fascism in the Early Twenties," Wiktor Sukiennicki, typed essay, 1967 (Box-folder 29: 9)
- Clippings and newspaper issues, 1959-1962 (Box-folder 29: 10)
  Includes a copy of New Poland that covers the new draft constitution of the Polish People's Republic and two article clippings from unknown publications.
- Plany obozów i historia Starobielsk i Ostaszków, undated (Box-folder 29: 11)
- Katyn, 1943-1951 (Box-folder 29: 12)
  Short reports covering Polish prisoners of war captured by Russia during the 1939 campaign, excerpts about the Sikorski-Mayski agreentment in 1941, and a copy of the official report from the United States concerning the need for a committee to conduct an investigation into the Katyn Massacre.
- Printed material, 1941-1944 (Box-folder 29: 13)
  Includes Naprzod ku zwyciestwu, zołnierze-Słowianie, k brat'yam ugnetennym slavyanam, and Słowianin. Printed booklets cover Slavic soldiers in World War II, the Polish Committee of Slavic London, and the Slavic Congress in Moscow.
- Katyn, printed material, 1940-1981 (Box-folder 29: 14)
  Includes a chapter excerpt written by Sukiennicki and a typescript, both printed in Polish and related to the history of Polish prisoners in the Soviet Union at the end of World War II.
- Katyn, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 30: 1-2)
  Relates to the Katyn Massacre and includes investigations, reports, memoranda, essays, book excerpts, and research notes.
- Bibliography and publications, undated (Box-folder 30: 3)
- Zwiazek polskich federalistow, 1950 (Box-folder 30: 4)
- Biographical materials, 1940-1956 (Box-folder 30: 5-6)
  Correspondence, memoranda, typescripts, and photographs related to Sukiennicki, in Polish and English.
- Maps, Polish prisoners of camp "Kozelsk,", 1939-1941 (Box-folder 30: 7)
- Biography, 1971-1985 (Box-folder 30: 8)
- 1983-1988 (Box-folder 30: 9)
  Includes typed bibliographies, correspondence, and an article written by Sukiennicki published in Kwartalnik Historyczny.
- Legal situation in Poland, 1950-1983 (Box-folder 30: 10)
- Polish collection at Hoover Institution Archives, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 30: 11)
- Publications, 1950-1993 (Box-folder 30: 12, 31: 1)
- Printed material, 1961-1978 (Box-folder 31: 2-3)
  Includes photocopied excerpts from Revue d'études comparatives est-ouest and article clippings from Tydzien Polski and Dziennik Polski.